[SPEAKER_01]: a little bit, then I'll test it and see how it goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the first thing I was going to ask you about was your, I have a story here that you had with Taylor Sprink back in 1938, and he spoke about your dad being a minstrel.
[SPEAKER_00]: I would rather not have that projected of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, could you repeat then about your mother and father, their families, where they were from?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, my father's family was from the genealogical reports.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were from England and Holland Dutch, but mainly England.
[SPEAKER_00]: They came over here, I don't know what year it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have the genealogy books in there.
[SPEAKER_00]: They've been there since around 1640 or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were quite, what shall I say, I don't mean to say patriotic, but they were quite American because of the reason they fought the American Revolution, and I am qualified as a
[SPEAKER_00]: As a matter of fact, I was a son of the American Revolution.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, I'm qualified to be the son of an officer in the American Revolution.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I was a son of the American Revolution here in Cincinnati until some nitwit wrote me a letter.
[SPEAKER_00]: about nine dollars that I owed for dues that I, to tell you the truth, I'd lost in all the papers you get, you know, and I didn't, wasn't conscious of it and forgot to pay it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the guy wrote me some kind of a snarky letter intimating that I didn't have the money or some god darn thing, so I wrote him back and told him that something to the effect that I was sorry that I hadn't paid him, but he
[SPEAKER_00]: The nine dollars now are just as good as something snarky, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I resigned from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had an ancestor who was 15 years old at the Battle of Bennington.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's Bennington, Vermont, too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, a very tenuous claim to that, too.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although none of us have... My father... One of my ancestors was supposed to have, according to my father,
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, you get those old folks like your father probably, and mine, and my grandfather, and all these other people, the biggest liars in the world, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: I like old ballplayers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, this is bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: He did distinguish for me, but as a boy, I was never interested in that stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know what your kids are.
[SPEAKER_00]: He pointed out some fellow that was in
[SPEAKER_00]: the guard, the honor guard that escorted Lafayette when he came over here to the White House or something like that, I forget what it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know what the heck.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get all these stories and then I do know that you see my, I was in the Hoyt Homestead
[SPEAKER_00]: around 1950, 1960.
[SPEAKER_00]: This would be in Manchester?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and part of it has been in the basement, but somebody else owns it.
[SPEAKER_00]: My cousin Russell was one of the trustees of Columbia University, and his two sisters, Grace and Frances, who never married, they used to call them bachelor ladies or whatever the heck you call them,
[SPEAKER_00]: were society entertainers.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, they played the harp and the harpsichord and all these things for the Vanderbilt's and this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they were with Elsie Janis in the First World War when she made that tour over there, you know, that was Grace and Francis Hoyt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they also made the Chautauqua circuit quite a lot with William Jennings Bryan, so they
[SPEAKER_00]: They were quite famous.
[SPEAKER_00]: They lived in the famous Dakota apartment house in the 70s on West 72nd and Central Park West.
[SPEAKER_00]: You may have heard of the Dakota, that's a famous apartment house.
[SPEAKER_00]: At any rate, they were quite prominent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Russell,
[SPEAKER_00]: Russell was quite also prominent as he never married either, but he was an inveterate baseball fan and a very fine fellow.
[SPEAKER_00]: He used to appear at the gates once in a while without my knowing it and say hello to me in New York.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he always, for some reason, they always kept their distance.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know why, but they did.
[SPEAKER_00]: except that one of the sisters invited us up, Mrs. Hoyden and herself, up for dinner at the Dakota House.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was very, very entrancing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They had all these antiques from Vermont, you know, in this apartment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they still had the house.
[SPEAKER_00]: They still had the house in... Well, they hadn't sold it yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't sell it till Russell died.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Russell was very close
[SPEAKER_00]: I forget the name of the fellow.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't think of the name and that aggravates me so darn much.
[SPEAKER_00]: The name of the family that gives the big dog show in New Jersey every year.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he's a very...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a national thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the biggest dog show in the country every year.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he's a Rockefeller associate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he was Russell's...
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't be Belmont, would it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was Russell's...
[SPEAKER_00]: executive, and he was also the administrator of his estate.
[SPEAKER_01]: These were your cousins now, this Russell and the two ladies?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the two sisters, yeah, Grace and Francis.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were your father's or mother's brother or sister?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, they related to my father.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Russell became violently ill and for years was incapacitated, and that sort of stripped the
[SPEAKER_00]: That end of the family, the money they had, then they had to sell the place in Vermont.
[SPEAKER_00]: A strange thing, Mrs. Hoyt and I always hoped that we'd get some fabulous antique because they were so patriotic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, every year you'd get the Christmas card.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of being a Christmas card, it would be a picture of the house or a picture of the interior.
[SPEAKER_00]: with a picture of the, some antiques in the corner, these high cupboards and these things worth thousands of dollars.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we were always hoping that we'd get something like that, just a relic of the Hoyt family.
[SPEAKER_00]: And nothing ever developed like that, except that one day when we lived, we had a house here in Cincinnati, and the mailman delivered a package one day, this is after Russell's death.
[SPEAKER_00]: I opened the package and it was an American flag and they out dropped a rose petal and what it actually was was the American flag that had covered the caskets you see and this is my inheritance from all these antiques that were supposed to have been up there in Manchester, Vermont.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their story is a very fascinating story.
[SPEAKER_00]: I always thought a lot of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did your father get into the Swift Company?
[SPEAKER_00]: Through my uncle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't ask me how my uncle got there because that was my father's sister's husband.
[SPEAKER_00]: My father originally was with an outfit called Mason Hanson.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think they were tailors.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say tailors, they weren't tailors as we know tailors.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were more like people that would make suits for Brooks Brothers, I mean, or provide cloth for Brooks Brothers or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he left there and went to L. Heller & Sons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, L. Heller & Sons, H-E-L-L-E-R. L. Heller & Sons, I guess it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: I put the S on there for
[SPEAKER_00]: a purpose, were the first, I shouldn't say this, everybody always says the first, but I was given to understand that they were, let's say, among the first, if not the first, importers or manufacturers, whatever it is, of synthetic, no, no, not synthetic,
[SPEAKER_00]: pearls, but they were deliberately grown.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you call those?
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not synthetic.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're pearls, but they're really bred, if you know what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not just haphazardly found.
[SPEAKER_00]: But my father left there because of the reason that there were so many sons in the family were taking over.
[SPEAKER_00]: There wasn't any place to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were going to go so high.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then once you got to that level, why then the sons to go, you know?
[SPEAKER_00]: But he was a great ball fan.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your father now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Huh?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your father, you're speaking?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, oh yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did he play ball?
[SPEAKER_00]: He played semi-pro ball in Brooklyn, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he helped build a ball field over there, one of the original ball fields, called Hawthorn Field in Flatbush.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Hawthorns used to play the, they used to play, well, they used to play all-star teams.
[SPEAKER_00]: And after the season, they'd play teams of big leaguers and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were pretty good, so I understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Had he lived in Chicago when he worked in the Swiss there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: We lived in Brooklyn all our lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were all buried in Brooklyn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Greenwood?
[SPEAKER_01]: Greenwood Cemetery.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where my grandparents were buried.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no more graves in Greenwood.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think so.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't buy anything unless somebody moves out of there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Greenwood Cemetery is a beautiful cemetery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it has here about your high school years, so that's pretty well covered, and how you became a pitcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: It mentions here about all these leagues that you played in, I guess, while in high school.
[SPEAKER_01]: Were there a number of leagues around Brooklyn there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the newspapers used to have leagues.
[SPEAKER_00]: There used to be the Brooklyn Times League and the Brooklyn Eagle League.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was another league, but I forget the name of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's Prospect Park here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, that's the parade grounds in Prospect Park.
[SPEAKER_00]: They had quite a number of people with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They had 20 diamonds on that place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we won most of the fellows that played on the
[SPEAKER_00]: The Brooklyn Times League and the Brooklyn Eagle League were members of the high school team, which we won the city championship, that sort of thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then in the off times, they played under the name of this other team, the Wyandottes.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were a pretty good ball club.
[SPEAKER_01]: Were you pitching at that time or playing?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I started as a second baseman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's kind of a joke story because this other team was being formed and in those days we didn't have organized leagues and things and organized like Napo and we didn't have those kind of things so to play with a team that had uniforms was rather unique and this team was going to have uniforms
[SPEAKER_00]: So I heard that they needed a pitcher, so I asked the guy, I asked the fellow, I said, do you need anybody?
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, yeah, we need a pitcher.
[SPEAKER_00]: I said, well, I'm a pitcher and I've never pitched a game in my life, but I can throw the ball well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I became a pitcher because they were going to have uniforms.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would have thought you'd been a pitcher right off the throne as hard as you did.
[SPEAKER_01]: The kids are too hard for the pitchers, aren't they?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, my father was an infielder.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a third baseman, so he wanted me to be a... You see, they were different days, different days.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is ridiculous to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are what you call trite utterances because everybody today says, oh, those were different days way back then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, of course, they were different.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, in Brooklyn in those days, in Flatbush, where I lived, there were no paved roads, very few.
[SPEAKER_00]: In front of my home on Hollis Street, Hawthorne Street, that street wasn't paved for a long, long while.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was later on, but it wasn't in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: And my father used to take me out in the center of the road and bounce the ball to me and I had to learn to stop it and all these ruts and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so you got a good education that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: There wasn't, they didn't... A few bruises here and there, huh?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they didn't have these polished diamonds that they have nowadays, so you had to learn... Monster turf, huh?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it says here that you were contacted by the Brooklyn Feds.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did that come about?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fifteen or sixteen?
[SPEAKER_00]: That is a bit of a, the mystery of that is, that's a bit of a mystery.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't remember who the person was who first, oh I know, if I'm not mistaken, and I forget his position, I can look it up, Fred Jackledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh, well that's okay, we'll talk about it later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, Fred Jacklidge, and Fred Jacklidge I think played in the Federal League if I'm not mistaken, and uh, or had played, and he was what, he used to play out in that, uh, work out in that parade grounds, and he called attention to somebody down in the, with the Brooklyn Feds, and had me go down and, and work out there one day with him, and Grover Land was a fellow,
[SPEAKER_00]: caught me in the tryout.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Grover Land, who was probably one of the most profane ballplayers that ever lived, recommended that the Brooklyn Feds sign me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the Brooklyn Feds didn't have any, and the Federal League didn't have any minor leagues per se, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: They had the Colonial League, which had New Haven in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was that in Organized Baseball, the Colonial League?
[SPEAKER_00]: The Colonial League belonged to the Federal League, and that's where the Organized Baseball didn't recognize the Federal League.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it got down to it, they wanted me to go to New Haven, but I was only 14 years old, and the family wouldn't let me go, see, which they were quite smart from that respect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Were you kind of thrilled, though?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I got to work out?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that they were interested in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh yes, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your dad probably was.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh yeah, it was a big deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: I went down and worked out with the Brooklyn Feds.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, that was a big deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was your mother interested in your baseball career?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh certainly, but she didn't want me to go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: She was very despondent when I did finally go away to play ball.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, I went away when I was 16 years old.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that was only a couple of... You were the youngest national leaguer until Nutsaw, is that true?
[SPEAKER_00]: That point should be cleared up, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, I was the youngest player to ever sign, the youngest boy to ever sign a contract.
[SPEAKER_00]: up until that time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that brought, consequently, a lot of publicity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, my dad had a sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the first contract I signed was not a pay-for-play contract.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was an optional contract, that if I decided to play professional ball, I would be the property of the New York Giants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did that make you a professional, an optional contract?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that didn't make me a professional, because I had not received any pay for that, or money.
[SPEAKER_00]: No money changes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that only lasted, it was, I signed in like August of 1915 and I was 16 in September.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the next spring, why the Giants wanted to know that I wanted to go away to play for money when I went to Lebanon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when, but now getting back to Knoxville for a moment,
[SPEAKER_00]: Knoxville was 15 when he signed and he was, I don't know if he was younger than me or that, he might have been younger than me, I guess he was.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on the other hand, he was the youngest to ever play in the big league, play in a big league game.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, I didn't play in a big league game until I was 18.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, so he was the youngest ever player at that time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there was, there's Fred Jacklis, you see, he was with the Philadelphia Nationals, Brooklyn Nationals, and he was with 1914, he was with the Baltimore Feds.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how he recommended me to the Brooklyn Feds, you see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why wouldn't he recommend you to Baltimore then, if he was with Baltimore?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, now that I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: In 1915 he was still with Baltimore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in 1916... Because the league folded right then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, in 1916 he didn't play.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I don't quite understand it, but nevertheless...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I didn't go to the Colonial League.
[SPEAKER_00]: They had a family meeting, and they decided that I couldn't go.
[SPEAKER_00]: which was a wise decision.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were a little disappointed, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I wasn't really.
[SPEAKER_00]: That proves that I didn't have enough understanding or awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see, in 1916 or 1915, that same year, I was pitching batting practice, 1915, for the Brooklyn Dodgers.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Giants came over to Brooklyn and
[SPEAKER_00]: Red Doon was a friend of my father's, or knew my father, and he was a coach with the Giants at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And my father asked him to look me over.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, Red Doon looked me over and McGraw asked me would I come up to the Giants and pitch them about practicing the polo grounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that sounds easy, but it required two or three changes of trolley cars and a couple of elevated
[SPEAKER_00]: train rides, and it took me two hours to get from my home in Brooklyn to the Polar Grounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's two hours up and two hours back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And doing this most of the summer, I wasn't playing in games in my own classification.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I was getting tired out.
[SPEAKER_00]: God, I pitch every day in batting practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just a kid, and I was worn down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And these long rides, I didn't get home till late at night.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't say late at night, but I got home after family and dinner and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so consequently, when I walked in one day to McGraw and told McGraw, I said, I can't do this any longer, Mr. McGraw.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not playing any games.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not getting any experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the trip is too long.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all I'm doing is pitching practice and nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: called the trainer, Ed Jackal, and they said, go get John Foster.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, John B.
[SPEAKER_00]: Foster was the secretary of the Giants.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, and John B.
[SPEAKER_00]: Foster came in.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, take this boy down and tomorrow meet.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, can you get your dad down to the office tomorrow?
[SPEAKER_00]: And I said, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, well, bring him down tomorrow morning.
[SPEAKER_00]: and have him there at 11 o'clock in the giant oval, which was those days down on 23rd Street.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where we met him down there the next day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when we signed the option.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you have a chance to show any real ability just in batting practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, could you really fire away there or weren't you supposed to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, McGraw wanted to sign.
[SPEAKER_01]: You must have seen something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You really had impressed him then, even though it was batting practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did you think of McGraw when you first ran into him?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, he was beyond belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: To me, he knew baseball.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, he was very profane, but very fair, very tough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, at least tough talking and tough acting.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still, with it all, a gentleman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mrs. McGraw was a perfect lady.
[SPEAKER_01]: Christy Matheson seemed such a gentleman.
[SPEAKER_01]: He and McGraw were pretty close, weren't they?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet they seemed a little bit different in their words.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't like Matheson.
[SPEAKER_00]: Matheson didn't say five words to me all the year and a half I was fooling around with him.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, all the time I was with the Giants.
[SPEAKER_00]: He did ask me, was I going to college, and I said no, I wasn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he seemed to lose interest.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't talk to me, hardly at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: I never had a great deal of respect for Matheson as a man.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, he may have been the finest fellow in the world, I don't know, but why should a kid 15 years old or 16 make a past judgment on somebody that's his age and stature?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he was almost through.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a matter of fact, he was through.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was his last year, I think, 16, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he came here to manage here.
[SPEAKER_00]: He asked you if you were going to college.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was going to ask you that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The best opportunity I had to go to college was Harry Hempstead was the owner of the Giants at the time and he was the chairman of the board of Lafayette Lehigh, now I forget which.
[SPEAKER_00]: board of directors, he wanted to know if I, he offered to pave my way through college and everything else, if I would go to Lehigh or Lafayette, I could get to Wichita.
[SPEAKER_00]: but I hadn't started my junior year in high school yet and I hated Latin and I hated mathematics and I would have to pass the Regents and all those and complete the two years and do a lot of catching up and studying and what the hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: The big story there is the fact that I was somewhat
[SPEAKER_00]: very efficient in writing and in the classic end of the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Miss Scoville, who was my English teacher, we called it English in those days, English teacher in school, grammar, in high school, didn't want me to go away to play ball.
[SPEAKER_00]: She offered to tutor me through the School of Journalism if I become a journalist instead of giving up the idea of playing ball and try to become a writer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she
[SPEAKER_00]: That never developed, but that was the other road that I've taken, and I always wondered what would have occurred.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even today, I wondered if I... what would have happened if I had taken the other road, you see.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've always, I mean, listening to your broadcasts, I mean, many years, you seem so well-read.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I read a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: I write a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so well spoken that it seemed to me you almost had a course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it kind of aggravates me today.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for instance,
[SPEAKER_00]: The four most recent books that have been published on baseball, I've done most of the collaborating with Bob Kramer and Bob Smith, who's a very good friend of mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a matter of fact, we still may do a book together on child and kid baseball.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Danny Mosedale, who wrote The 27 Yankees and didn't do a very good job.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a priest up in Notre Dame.
[SPEAKER_00]: Marshall Schmelzer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I know him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's a fellow historian.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why should he write about Begoo?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does he know about Begoo?
[SPEAKER_00]: I told Creamer nicely, I like Bob Creamer very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can show you a letter from Creamer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a little difficult to find, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nevertheless, where he said, you told me in Palm Beach I couldn't write this in five years, and after five years I wouldn't even have it then.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, you were right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, I've written a book.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, I don't know whether I'm right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: I told him, I said, you couldn't write Babe Ruth, nobody could write Babe Ruth unless you live with them and could smell them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that you're unable to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But so many people write the untruths on Ruth.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's been more untruths written about Ruth than any man that I know of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they persist in their false delineations of this fellow that they play spindly legs
[SPEAKER_00]: and he didn't have...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll show you pictures of Ruth with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'd want to see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they called him Fat, and he wasn't fat at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was fat the last couple of years he played, but he wasn't fat in his prime.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I don't want to get into that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's too...
[SPEAKER_01]: The trouble with that is, this is the...
[SPEAKER_01]: In future years, it'll be that image of Ruth which will survive, because they've got it in print, you see, as wrong as it may be.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the official word, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unfortunate about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was going to write a contrary opinion, but you get into that thing, you get into it with Aaron and Ruth.
[SPEAKER_00]: and the differences and nobody attacks it from the truthful angle because they don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're writing about things they don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: One little, which they do know, but they're not aware of.
[SPEAKER_00]: For instance, they write pieces about Ruth and the Yankee Stadium and the right field pavilion and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody realized the right field pavilion wasn't there when Ruth was playing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see?
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody believes that the...
[SPEAKER_00]: The Polaroid, you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, the Yankee Stadium.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right period for bidding wasn't there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where Maris hit his 61st home run.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That wasn't added on until...
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't realize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: That wasn't added on until Ruth was away from there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that gets utterly ridiculous to hear people talk about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can appreciate your frustration at reading that kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure it must bother you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing you can do about it really.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing you can do about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing you can do about it at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: My opinion of the thing is that when you go 3,500 more times at bat than the other guy, that's not a record.
[SPEAKER_00]: In my opinion, you might get more home runs, which he did.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he, Aaron, is deservedly entitled to all the rewards and the credit that could possibly be due anybody that could perform such a feat.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nevertheless, if Ruth had gone about 3,500 more times, you'd get 250 more home runs.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, this gets ridiculous after a while.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I have a letter here.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is from New Jersey.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm putting together a series of yearbooks on the great teams of baseball.
[SPEAKER_00]: The expense is entirely mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, isn't that nice?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm supposed to pay for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: One of the teams I've selected, the 27 Yankees of which you were up, this just came today, you were an integral member.
[SPEAKER_00]: And my request is this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you take a few minutes of your time?
[SPEAKER_00]: This would take three hours to write.
[SPEAKER_00]: to give me some of your remembrances of the teams for me to include in the yearbook.
[SPEAKER_00]: In particular, I'd be interested in the 27 Yanks pitching staff and your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: A staff that, in my opinion, is greatly underrated and overshadowed because of the awesome hitters that made the team famous.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was it like to pitch for a team so likely to give you all the hitting support you'd ever need?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was the pitching staff underrated?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you and the other pitchers ever feel overlooked or unappreciated because you
[SPEAKER_00]: of all the attention being heaped on Ruth Gehrig and so forth, did you realize that you were part of something really special?
[SPEAKER_00]: A team that would be someday considered by historians as baseball's all-time greatest?
[SPEAKER_00]: Any thoughts you may have and so forth, he'd appreciate.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, I should sit down and write.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, if we take the book, you see, and if we look at 1927, he discovered that we pitched the most complete games of any pitching staff in our league, 87, as a matter of
[SPEAKER_00]: No, we didn't at that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Chicago did, 85.
[SPEAKER_00]: We had 82.
[SPEAKER_00]: We allowed the least number of base on balls, 409.
[SPEAKER_00]: We didn't strike out the most.
[SPEAKER_00]: We had the most shutouts, 11.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we had the lowest earned run average in the league, 320.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he looked those up, you see, he discovered that the iron run average, we led the league in iron runs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So how would the pitching staff be so overshadowed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I have one of those, remember those rain delay broadcasts you made?
[SPEAKER_01]: They put on a record.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you make more than one record?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just have the one.
[SPEAKER_01]: I never could get a copy of the second one.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think there are any.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have one, but... That's the only one, maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's possibly the only one left.
[SPEAKER_00]: The first one was taken off the air, and it isn't...
[SPEAKER_00]: It stutters through, as people do when they talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: The second one was made in a studio out in Hollywood.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's stories on...
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember you mentioned your sail to New Orleans and you didn't report when you went back.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm curious about the Baltimore dry docks and how you happened to go there.
[SPEAKER_01]: What kind of a setup was this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that was during the war.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, it was after World War I, and that's a misconception too, a little bit of a misconception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Interesting though.
[SPEAKER_00]: During World War I, a great many of the leagues broke up because they couldn't continue.
[SPEAKER_00]: There wasn't any patronage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Too many players.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the players were being drafted.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was in the Southern League in 1918, and it broke up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I went to the
[SPEAKER_00]: Newark International League, and that was switched up to Hamilton, Ontario played up there, and all this sort of thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So at the end of the 1918, the league closed down at the end of the season.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, the war ended, but it didn't end until November, two months after the... Now, a lot of the shipyards that were...
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you call it?
[SPEAKER_00]: I forget the name.
[SPEAKER_00]: A contributory industry.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you got into some industry...
[SPEAKER_01]: The worker fight order said you had to either get in the jigguards or steel mills.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they had leagues of their own, and a lot of these pro ball players went into those leagues, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, after the war, things had gone so well in those leagues that they continued them.
[SPEAKER_00]: and in 1919 the shipyard league is still going with the Baltimore Dry Docks and the shipyards around Philadelphia and Brooklyn and these other shipyards and the leagues continued.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I had quite an argument with Newark at the time
[SPEAKER_00]: and McGraw and all this sort of thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arthur Irwin, who was probably the most disgusting man that I ever knew of, and I never wished any man ill luck, but nevertheless, I hated that guy, and he fell off the boat in the Fall River line and was drowned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who was he?
[SPEAKER_00]: He was the manager of the Newark club, and he didn't like me and I didn't like him.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had a Montreal shirt,
[SPEAKER_00]: and another pair of pants, and a guy with some cap, they always awful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at the end of the season, my three years was up.
[SPEAKER_00]: In short, a big league club was allowed to send you out for three years.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then they had to keep you or trade you or get rid of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: My three years was up, so they traded me to Rochester for a fellow named Al Nixon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I didn't want to go to, and I thought, well, I'd never won in the minor leagues, and the minor leagues, I'd had enough of the minor leagues.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the rubber company from Chickapee Falls, Massachusetts, and I forget the name of it, it was either, it wasn't Firestone, or it was one of those big companies, came down and asked me if I would come up there and pitch for their
[SPEAKER_01]: Not to work, just to pitch?
[SPEAKER_01]: And work.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rubber company wanted me to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were going to teach me the rubber industry.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it wouldn't have been any bad deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: They made tires, and they were in a very good outfit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I thought it over, and I decided not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't want to pay that much money anyway, and I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I got this offer to come down to Baltimore and go to work for the Baltimore Dry Docks and pitch for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: which I did.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'd have to actually work on the ships?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, we'd make a pass at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You had to do some work.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we had to go to work every morning and you had to be there at 8 o'clock or whatever time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't play ball on weekends only or one weekday?
[SPEAKER_00]: We would play and work and we played Saturdays and Sundays and played once during the weeks.
[SPEAKER_00]: We worked out every day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we had a pretty good ball club.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a matter of fact, that was the
[SPEAKER_00]: That was a revelation in itself, because we had Lefty Russell, whom you wouldn't recognize, but he was at one time a very prominent acquisition by somebody.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was an $11,000 beauty at one point, Lefty Russell.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wasn't even a pitcher, but he played for his base there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I forget the... And we had...
[SPEAKER_00]: They were all pro-ball players, all of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bill Zimmerman, all of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every one of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Polk Whalen and Norman McNeil went to the Red Sox from there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how I went to the Red Sox.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I wound up pitching for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the beginning of the 1919 season?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is where it becomes involved, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a little hard to explain.
[SPEAKER_00]: The big leagues and the minor leagues had a fight.
[SPEAKER_00]: The big leagues did not recognize the reserve clause in the minor league contracts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if you hadn't signed a minor league contract, the minor leagues had no claim to your services.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were the same as a free agent, which I was.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I played.
[SPEAKER_00]: and pitched for the Baltimore Dry Docks, and we beat a damn near everybody, and including the Cincinnati Reds.
[SPEAKER_00]: I shut them out 1-0.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the year they won the penalty.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they came down there, and I shut them out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Tom Swope, who used to write down here, went back and told Pat Moran there was a good-looking young pitcher that he should get that shut his ball club out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Moran said he didn't want to fool around with any kids or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: At any rate, the Norman McNeil, the catcher that we had, went to the Red Sox and told Ed Barrow, who was the manager of the Red Sox, about me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the Red Sox came to Washington, Barrow asked me, through Norman McNeil, to come over and pitch batting practice for a couple of days, which I did.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then about three weeks later, I got a
[SPEAKER_00]: A wire from Barrow asked me to come to Boston and sign a contract that if I come to Boston and work out a day where you sign me to a contract.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I went to Boston and I told them that I would sign the contract, that we would put a clause in the contract that I would start again within four days after I arrived there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wasn't going to sit around on any more benches or be farmed out in professional baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a rather unusual claim.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, you're a fresh kid.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I said, well, I'm sorry, but that's the way it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's either going to be that or I quit pro ball.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not going to be fooling around with professional baseball.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he said, oh, I never heard anything like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: At any rate, he started me and I beat Detroit 2-1 in 12 innings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pitch against Cobb in your first game?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was funny too because in those days, two or three batters were allowed to stand up waiting their turn to bat.
[SPEAKER_00]: At least a couple always did.
[SPEAKER_00]: They'd stand and now they have a batting circle, but in those days there wasn't any batting circle.
[SPEAKER_00]: They stood where they wanted to, and Cobb, whoever was hitting ahead of him, I think it was Bobby Beach, called me every dirty name he could think of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then when it was his turn to bat, he stepped in the center of the home plate and turned his back on me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he stood in the center of the plate with his back to me for, it seemed like five minutes, but it was, I guess, only a minute or two.
[SPEAKER_00]: And George Moriarty, who hated Cobb and was a second base umpire, used to play for Detroit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Came in and told Cobb to get the hell around there and get going.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was no plate umpire?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh yes, yeah, but the plate umpire didn't have anything to do with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There were only two umpires then.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Moriarty, he took the matter in his own hands.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he turned Cobb around and went, Cobb, get up the bat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why, then I stepped off the rubber.
[SPEAKER_00]: and let Cobb stand there for about five minutes, and then I got this profanity all over again, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: He tripled in the eighth inning and tied the score, but one-to-one.
[SPEAKER_00]: We beat him two-to-one in 12 innings, and we won it peculiarly, and it seemed to be indicative of my entire career because Everett Scott
[SPEAKER_00]: Got on second base with one out, and I don't know if it was one out, I guess it was just one out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But anyway, they put in Mike McNally, who could run pretty fast, and I think to run for Scott, and the next batter hit a ball at the shortstop, and McNally tried to score all the way from second base on the infield out, which you don't see much of today, and he was run down between third and home.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Eddie Ainsmith, the catcher of Detroit, didn't have the ball and bumped into McNally and knocked him aside.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was interference and they allowed to run the score and we beat them 2 to 1.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the way I won my first game.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's real that one, huh?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that was a... Well, you're talking about Barrow and the contract he signed with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: You had this, put in your contract you were going to start in four days and he agreed to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What did you like Ed Barrow?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, did I like him?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh yes, very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: He brought me over to the Yankees.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to ask you about Harry Frazee, did you meet him?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: the African man.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll tell you an interesting story.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, this all has to do with Ruth.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were writing a book on Ruth, if I was, there was so much to Ruth that had to do with the entire world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ruth that wasn't confined in a home run circle or atmosphere and isolated in that category.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things happened to that guy.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a man of the entire world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like them shouting in World War II, Babe Ruth's this, that, or whatever, the Japanese.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, he was a world figure in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now I've lost... You're talking about Fray Z. Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ruth was sold to New York for over $100,000 because of part of a loan that Rupert had made to
[SPEAKER_00]: Frazee.
[SPEAKER_00]: Frazee paid back partial, I think it was $300,000, but $110,000 was still owing me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rupert took Ruth, I think, off the Red Sox.
[SPEAKER_00]: This may not be exactly the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is the truth, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I may not have the facts exactly right.
[SPEAKER_00]: At any rate, Ruth came to the Yankees for the money.
[SPEAKER_00]: In 1920, Ruth was with the Yankees, but in 1920, we, the Red Sox, played the Giants on the way up and we played a series with the Giants in the Polar Grounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: The, uh, Frazee, uh, posted a notice on the bulletin board that his, he had a show down on Broadway and
[SPEAKER_00]: The members of the Red Sox ball club were invited to come to the show.
[SPEAKER_00]: All they had to do was identify themselves at the box office and there were tickets there for them, see?
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I'm not quite certain of the name of the show.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's easy to find out, but I believe the name of the show was, I'll Say She Is.
[SPEAKER_00]: I believe that was it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either that or that was a Marx Brothers show.
[SPEAKER_00]: I forget which it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nevertheless, I think that was it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was a straight comedy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Produced by Harry Frazee.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, it was actually produced by the money that Frazee got for Ruth, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: a part alone of this business.
[SPEAKER_00]: And four years later, the show is produced again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the show?
[SPEAKER_00]: No No Nanette, except the music.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'll say she has set the music.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what happens?
[SPEAKER_00]: Indirectly, Ruth is responsible for one of the greatest shows that was ever on Broadway.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is this right?
[SPEAKER_00]: The Sailor Ruth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then that's produced here a couple of years ago, Ruby Keeler making her second appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fellow had a... his influences ran in all directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've had a couple of interviews with Fred Lee, remember?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, very well.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's on the Old Times Committee.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says that Fray Z had so many flops on Broadway that he had to sell all you fellows to New York to recoup his losses.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you know about that?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know anything about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that right?
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't hear anything about that?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That could be true.
[SPEAKER_01]: That could be true.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think Fred wanders off once in a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think so too, but he was quite close to the theater.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fred really was.
[SPEAKER_01]: He attended the theater and knew a lot of theatrical people, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: It could be true.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wouldn't doubt that at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think Frazee was always short on money.
[SPEAKER_01]: He lived right down the street from Rupert, I guess.
[SPEAKER_01]: His Broadway or his New York office was close to the Yankee office, I guess.
[SPEAKER_01]: The IDI guy, he was over there a good bit of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, everybody was.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, people don't understand today the public relations of Angle.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, there were 14 newspapers in New York at the time, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And each office, like the Giants and the Yankees, had hospitality rooms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you went up there in the afternoon in the wintertime,
[SPEAKER_00]: You'd find 12 and 13, why the place would be crowded with baseball people, see, and all these stories would take place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it wouldn't be uncommon to get any type of stories.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just loaded with baseball people.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was always an open bar.
[SPEAKER_00]: doing prohibition, and this was very much of an attraction, these places.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was Frey Z. liked by the Boston people, being an absentee owner?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did they think much of that or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't think much about it, I don't think.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wasn't what I would call a popular owner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, how did you fellows on the team feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, we never saw him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I know when he began selling every bit of New York.
[SPEAKER_00]: What the hell?
[SPEAKER_00]: We didn't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: We were sold ourselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: When Ruth was sold, you felt left behind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was the first one to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're left behind now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you feel you were losing somebody?
[SPEAKER_01]: And wasn't this kind of a betrayal of your fine team?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mays was the first to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mays objected to... Yeah, I remember that, Mays.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, I'm doing a biography of Ban Johnson.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a... had some Marietta Lynx, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Carl Mays case, of course, is what marked Ban Johnson's downfall.
[SPEAKER_01]: When Mays quit the club and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you see that book on Carl Mays?
[SPEAKER_01]: I haven't seen that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought of getting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it a fair book, would you say?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I wouldn't think so.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think it's well written and they tell big lies about me in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know it's put out by a vanity press.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you have to pay to get it published.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a good way to publish that book.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm suspicious of those kind of books.
[SPEAKER_00]: The book, I have the book if you want it, if I can find it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the last chapter tells where Huggins said that I was this, that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Huggins never said any such thing about me at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Huggins was a good friend of mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I always thought the world of Huggins, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Mays was the first to go, then Ruth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, as far as the money was concerned, the trade was four for four.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, when you get down to it, this is where I think Lee was a little bit off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which trade now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Involving yourself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there was Harper and myself and Shang and McNally were traded for Sam Vick and Muddy Rule and Del Pratt and Herb Thornmalen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it was four for four.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not quite equal though, four, was it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I don't know that, but I wasn't approved in pitching yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wally Shang, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: Shang was a pinwheel catcher.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, Muddy Rue was another catcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, this Mays business.
[SPEAKER_01]: You came up in mid-1919 season, didn't you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Were you with the team the day Mays walked off the field?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he had already gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wanted to ask about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's so important in my Ben Johnson story.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just want to know what the player's reaction might have been.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, push the thing down.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, this is the most malicious thing that I have read.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know whether I wrote to him or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: He must be disgusted with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: In what way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it just his treatment of Mays?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, well, I am not interested in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know more about Mays than this guy does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mays used to lie up in the bed with me, I mean on the other bed, and talk about knocking guys down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all this, they don't let them get too close to the plate.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're taking the bread and butter out of your hand, out of your mouth, and all this kind of stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: And keeping it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did he throw hitters, do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the strange thing is, I don't think he threw a chopper.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think he told me he threw a curve.
[SPEAKER_00]: He told me, and I'll swear to God,
[SPEAKER_00]: I swear to God that he told me that he hit him with a curveball.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't throw curveballs at guys.
[SPEAKER_01]: Roger Peckinpah, I've talked to him a couple of times.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's in Cleveland now where I live.
[SPEAKER_00]: He played shortstop with the Yankees that day.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was right behind that pitch.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says that pitch that hit Chatelain was a strike.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you see, what people don't realize, it's Fuster.
[SPEAKER_00]: and Chapman stood at the plate with their heads over the outside corner.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, nobody goes, this is what I have against baseball books and baseball writers.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, they don't know these things and they don't conclude them.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're going to write things, be objective and write things on both sides of the question.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is my opinion, don't you think so?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says in here that
[SPEAKER_00]: And Carl said, Rube Marquardt was a great pitcher and I'm glad he made it, but my record is so far superior to his that it makes me wonder.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess the answer is they don't like me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that the Hall of Fame you're speaking of?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I've got to say that I wouldn't want to be quoted on this, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody has ever mentioned
[SPEAKER_00]: Carl Mays in that respect.
[SPEAKER_00]: They've never said, as a matter of fact, his name came up for a qualification this year in the Hall of Fame.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you on the old-timers committee?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And nobody has mentioned the hitting of Chapman or anything else about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's never been a nil word said about
[SPEAKER_00]: see what I mean about keeping him out of the Hall of Fame or anything of that nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no doubt about what the fellow was an excellent pitcher and one of the better pitchers but he did things, he did some things that one of the
[SPEAKER_00]: sad things was, and I felt sorry for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have kind of a sentimental streak, I guess, in me, but we were on the bench.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, the Athletics had never, I don't know his record against them, but he had, the Athletics hadn't beaten him in years, or something or other, and he got on bad with Miller Huggins, and he beat the Athletics in
[SPEAKER_00]: Philadelphia three to two, if I'm not mistaken.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he didn't pitch again in two weeks.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we were over this in 19... What year was this?
[SPEAKER_00]: 19...
[SPEAKER_00]: I could look it up and see what year it went to the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know if he finished the season or not with us that year, but he was sent here to Cincinnati, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: 22 or so.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was 23, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: And...
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh...
[SPEAKER_00]: We got in trouble, the Yanks got in trouble.
[SPEAKER_00]: Miller Huggins said to George Pipgrass, who was just a kid on the club at that time, go down to the bullpen and get ready.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Carl said, what's the matter with me, Oak?
[SPEAKER_00]: See, there was a discipline on the Yankee bench nothing like any other team in the history of the game.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like the third
[SPEAKER_00]: You sat there and you paid attention to the game.
[SPEAKER_00]: You didn't kid around.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was silence and you paid attention to what was going on, believe me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so he says, what's the matter with me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Hug and hug, turned around to him and said, Carl, I even forgot you were on the club.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this guy had won 27 games at one time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see what happened overnight, these are the things that are not known.
[SPEAKER_00]: Over in 1921, we were playing the athletics in Philadelphia.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will say it's one of the last series of the season, either the next to last or the third from last.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the Yankees' first pennant.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're only a game and a half ahead of Cleveland.
[SPEAKER_00]: We needed the games, and we got in trouble, and Carl being so good against the Athletics, he had pitched with one day's rest, but that's the year he won 27 games.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hugg asked him to go down to the bullpen because our pitcher was in trouble, and Carl said, no, he said, I've done enough pitching for the year.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's the Yankees about to win the pennant or something, and he wouldn't go down to the bullpen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Huggins hated him from then on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then there was something about some gambling, I don't know what it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you must have gotten along pretty well with him, been in the room with him quite a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he made a lot of trouble.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yours got along well with people.
[SPEAKER_00]: He made a lot of trouble with Nutworth at this point.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had another one at this point.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he would try to isolate me from the rest and everybody else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Carl was a troublemaker.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now here it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The record shows you this and that.
[SPEAKER_00]: In 1921, Carl led the league with wins 27 and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now this is the worst thing that I've ever seen in print about myself and it's so absolutely, it says Wade Hoyt and Cobb.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now back to the Yankees.
[SPEAKER_00]: The early Yankees, any man that could have won with them
[SPEAKER_00]: Pennock and Bush pitched in the World Series nine years before they became Yankees.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bush had also pitched on, so Huggins got all the credit from the newspapers and a lot of abuse from the players.
[SPEAKER_00]: The abuse was his own fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was his own fault because he reacted to situations just like he didn't have any guts to make the decisions and the players let him know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when things would go bad for us, as they occasionally did, Huggins would sit on the bench with his head down, holding his hands, moaning, oh, what happened, or when he
[SPEAKER_00]: walk up and down in front of the bench with his head held in his hands and some of the players would spit tobacco juice on his stockings as he walked by.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, this is all Spite stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't remember that at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can remember Huggins.
[SPEAKER_00]: Huggins had what we call traveling palsy or neuritis or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: He couldn't keep his legs still and his leg would go like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was an affliction, really, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Babe Ruth had no use from the early days, and neither did Big Bob Musil.
[SPEAKER_00]: They called him Little Boy, and Babe used to ask real sarcastically, what now, Little Boy, what?
[SPEAKER_00]: I never heard of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I never heard of that in my life, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Babe never forgave Huck for that $5,000 fine, so and so, and so and so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Miller attempted to humiliate Wade Hoyt, too.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wade got into one of those streaks where he couldn't get anybody out in the first inning, which was true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present-day fans remember how early Wynn had a start like that with the Shy Sox a few years back, and also Gary Peters' rough time with the Red Sox in 70.
[SPEAKER_00]: When Wade was having his troubles, Huggins called him gutless in front of the whole team.
[SPEAKER_00]: Huggins never did anything of the sort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Huggins and I were good friends.
[SPEAKER_00]: I felt that Huggins was a father to me in this business, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one time when Wade had gotten shelled out, Huggins even ordered him not to go into the clubhouse until the other players had dressed and gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was pretty rough treatment for Wade, who had more guts in his little finger than Huggins had in his whole body.
[SPEAKER_00]: I got so sore to Huggins that I yelled at him that I wouldn't go until Hoyt did.
[SPEAKER_00]: Furthermore, I told him I was going to room with Wade.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do and I'll fine you $250, he snapped at me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go ahead and fine me $250, I shot back at him, but I'm going to room with him whether you like it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Went to the room with him and hugged finally $250, but I knew what was wrong with the boy.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was only a kid just over 20 years old and he was too good looking for his own good and what he needed was somebody to sit down on him in the after hours, especially the night before he was to pitch.
[SPEAKER_00]: I sat on him the first night, if I remember correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was in Detroit and we were going to our room after a big dinner when Wade was resting on the bed looking at a book when I casually walked over to the door and locked it and was tucking a key into my
[SPEAKER_00]: The trowel was in his pocket when he looked up in surprise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hey, Carl, what are you doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: What am I doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'm just locking up for the night.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe you don't know it, but we've got a golf date early in the morning at the Detroit Country Club, and you're going to need plenty of sleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I've got a date tonight.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've got a girl coming in on the interurban trolley.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the goddamnedest story I ever heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did Mary's tell him that he's dispersed?
[SPEAKER_00]: He must have told it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, well, let her turn around and go home on the interurban trolley, Carl.
[SPEAKER_00]: I never heard of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't do that, I gotta meet him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you want to go through that door, you'll have to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You mean you'd fight to stop me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I'll fight to stop you.
[SPEAKER_01]: He must have got it from Mays, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Certainly he did.
[SPEAKER_01]: But did Mays make these things up?
[SPEAKER_01]: He must have made them up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe his memory was beginning to play tricks on him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what was he like to room with all those times?